I want you to imagine two couples in the middle of 1979 on the exact same day at the exact
same moment each conceiving a baby.
So two couples each conceiving one baby.
I don't want you to spend too much time imagining the conception because if you spend all that
time imagining that conception you're not going to listen to me.
So just imagine that for a moment and in this scenario I want to imagine that in one case
the sperm is carrying a Y chromosome meeting that X chromosome of the egg and in the other
case the sperm is carrying an X chromosome meeting the X chromosome of the egg.
Both are viable, both take off.
We'll come back to these people later.
So I wear two hats in most of what I do.
As the one hat I do history of anatomy.
I'm an historian by training and what I study in that case is the way that people have dealt
with anatomy, meaning human bodies, animal bodies, how they dealt with bodily fluids,
concepts of bodies, how they thought about bodies.
The other hat that I've worn in my work is as an activist, as a patient advocate or I
sometimes say as an inpatient advocate for people who are patients of doctors.
In that case what I've worked with is people who have body types that challenge social
norms.
So some of what I've worked on for example is people who are conjoined twins, two people
within one body.
Some of what I've worked on is people who have dwarfism, so people who are much shorter
than typical.
And a lot of what I've worked on is people who have atypical sex, so people who don't
have the standard male or the standard female body types.
And as a general term we can use the term intersex for this.
Intersex comes in a lot of different forms.
I'll just give you a few examples of the types of ways you can have sex that isn't standard
for male or female.
So in one instance you can have somebody who has an XY chromosomal basis and that SRY gene
on the Y chromosome tells the protogonads which we all have in the fetal life to become
testes.
In the fetal life those testes are pumping out testosterone.
But because this individual lacks receptors to hear that testosterone the body doesn't
react to the testosterone and this is a syndrome called androgen insensitivity syndrome.
So lots of levels of testosterone but no reaction to it.
As a consequence the body develops more along the female typical path.
When the child is born she looks like a girl.
She is a girl.
She is raised as a girl and it's often not until she hits puberty and she's growing and
developing breasts but she's not getting her period that somebody figures out something's
up here and they do some tests and figure out that instead of having ovaries inside
in a uterus she actually has testes inside and she has a Y chromosome.
Now what's important to understand is you may think of this person as really being male
but they're really not.
Females like males have in our bodies something called the adrenal glands.
They're in the back of our body and the adrenal glands make androgens which are a masculinizing
hormone.
Most females like me, I believe myself to be a typical female, I don't actually know
my chromosomal makeup but I think I'm probably typical.
Most females like me are actually androgen sensitive.
We're making androgens and we're responding to androgens.
The consequence is that somebody like me has actually had a brain exposed to more androgens
than the woman born with testes who has androgen insensitivity syndrome.
So sex is really complicated.
It's not just that intersex people are in the middle of all the sex spectrum.
In some ways they can be all over the place.
For example, a few years ago I got a call from a man who was 19 years old who was born
a boy, raised a boy, had a girlfriend, had sex with his girlfriend, had a life as a guy
and had just found out that he had ovaries and a uterus inside.
What he had was an extreme form of a condition called congenital adrenal hyperplasia.
He had XX chromosomes and in the womb his adrenal glands were in such high gear that
it created essentially a masculine hormonal environment and as a consequence his genitals
were masculinized, his brain was subject to the more typical masculine component of
hormones and he was born looking like a boy.
Nobody suspected anything and it was only when he had reached the age of 19 that he
began to have enough medical problems actually from menstruating internally that doctors
figured out that in fact he was female internally.
Okay, so just one more quick example of a way you can have intersex.
Some people who have XX chromosomes develop what are called ovotustes which is when you
have ovarian tissue with testicular tissue wrapped around it.
We're not exactly sure why that happens.
So sex can come in lots of different varieties.
The reason that children with these kinds of bodies whether it's dwarfism or it's conjoined
twinning or it's an intersex type are often normalized by surgeons is not because it actually
leaves them better off in terms of physical health.
In many cases people are actually perfectly healthy.
The reason they're often subject to various kinds of surgeries is because they threaten
our social categories.
Our system has been based typically on the idea that a particular kind of anatomy comes
with a particular identity.
So we have the concept that what it means to be a woman is to have a female identity.
What it means to be a black person is allegedly to have an African anatomy in terms of your
history.
And so we have this terribly simplistic idea and when we're faced with a body that actually
presents us something quite different it startles us in terms of those categorizations.
So we have a lot of very romantic ideas in our culture about individualism.
And our nation is really founded on a very romantic concept of individualism.
Well you can imagine how startling then it is when you have children who are born who
are two people inside of one body.
Where I ran into the most kind of heat from this most recently was last year when the
South African runner Caster Semenya had her sex called into question at the International
Games in Berlin.
I had a lot of journalists calling me asking me which is the test they're going to run
that will tell us whether or not Caster Semenya is male or female.
And I had to explain to the journalists there isn't such a test.
In fact we now know that sex is complicated enough that we have to admit nature doesn't
draw the line for us between male and female or between male and intersex and female and
intersex.
We actually draw that line on nature.
So what we have is a sort of situation where the farther our science goes the more we have
to admit to ourselves that these categories that we thought of as stable anatomical categories
that mapped very simply to stable identity categories are a lot more fuzzy than we thought.
And it's not just in terms of sex.
It's also in terms of race which turns out to be vastly more complicated than our terminology
has allowed.
As we look we get into all sorts of sort of uncomfortable areas.
We look for example about the fact that we share at least 95% of our DNA with chimpanzees.
What are we to make of the fact that we differ from them only really by a few nucleotides?
And as we get farther and farther with our science we get more and more into a discomforted
zone where we have to acknowledge that the simplistic categories we've had are probably
overly simplistic.
So we're seeing this in all sorts of places in human life.
One of the places we're seeing it for example in our culture today in the United States
today is battles over the beginning of life and the end of life.
We have difficult conversations about at what point we decide a body becomes a human
such that it has a different right than a fetal life.
We have very difficult conversations nowadays probably not out in the open as much as within
medicine about the question of when somebody's dead.
In the past our ancestors never had to struggle so much with this question of when somebody
was dead.
At most they'd stick a feather on somebody's nose and if it twitched they didn't bury them
yet.
If it stopped twitching you buried them.
But today we have a situation where we want to take vital organs out of beings and give
them to other beings.
And as a consequence we're stuck with having to struggle with this really difficult question
about who's dead.
And this leads us to a really difficult situation where we don't have such simple categories
as we've had before.
Now you might think that all this breaking down of categories would make somebody like
me really happy.
I'm a political progressive.
I defend people with unusual bodies but I have to admit to you that it makes me nervous.
Knowing that these categories are really much more unstable than we thought makes me tense.
And it makes me tense from the point of view of thinking about democracy.
So in order to tell you about that tension I have to first admit to you that I'm a huge
fan of the founding fathers.
I know they were racist.
I know they were sexist.
But they were great.
I mean they were so brave and so bold and so radical in what they did that I find myself
watching that cheesy musical 1776 every few years and it's not because of the music which
is totally forgettable.
It's because of what happened in 1776 with the founding fathers.
The founding fathers were from my point of view the original anatomical activists.
And this is why.
What they rejected was an anatomical concept and replaced it with another one that was
radical and beautiful and held us for 200 years.
So as you will recall what our founding fathers were rejecting was a concept of monarchy.
And the monarchy was basically based on a very simplistic concept of anatomy.
The monarchs of the old world didn't have a concept of DNA but they did have a concept
of birthright.
They had a concept of blue blood.
They had the idea that the people who would be in political power should be in political
power because of the blood being passed down from grandfather to father to son and so forth.
The founding fathers rejected that idea and they replaced it with a new anatomical concept
and that concept was all men are created equal.
They leveled that playing field and decided the anatomy that mattered was the commonality
of anatomy not the difference in anatomy and that was a really radical thing to do.
Now they were doing it in part because they were part of an enlightenment system where
two things were growing up together and that was democracy growing up but it was also science
growing up at the same time.
It's really clear if you look at the history of the founding fathers a lot of them were
very interested in science and they were interested in a concept of a naturalistic world.
They were moving away from supernatural explanations and they were rejecting things like a supernatural
concept of power where it transmitted because of a very vague concept of birthright.
They were moving towards a naturalistic concept and if you look for example in the Declaration
of Independence they talk about nature and nature's God.
They don't talk about God and God's nature.
They're talking about the power of nature to tell us who we are.
So as part of that they were coming to us with a concept that was about anatomical commonality
and in doing so they were really setting up in a beautiful way the civil rights movement
for the future.
They didn't think of it that way but they did it for us and it was great.
So what happened years afterwards?
What happened was women for example who wanted the right to vote took the founding fathers
concept of anatomical commonality being more important than anatomical difference and said
the fact that we have a uterus and ovaries is not significant enough in terms of a difference
to mean that we shouldn't have the right to vote, the right to full citizenship, the right
to own property, et cetera, et cetera.
And women successfully argued that.
Next came the successful civil rights movement where we found people like Sojourner Truth,
you know, talking about ain't I a woman.
We find men on the marching lines of the civil rights movement saying I am a man.
Again people of color appealing to a commonality of anatomy over a difference of anatomy.
Again successfully.
We see the same thing with the disability rights movement.
The problem is of course that as we begin to look at all that commonality we have to
begin to question why we maintain certain divisions.
Now mind you I want to maintain some divisions anatomically in our culture.
For example I don't want to give a fish the same rights as a human.
I don't want to say we give up entirely on anatomy.
I don't want to say five year olds should be allowed to consent to sex or consent to
marry.
So there are some anatomical divisions that make sense to me and that I think we should
retain.
But the challenge is trying to figure out which ones they are and why do we retain them
and do they have meaning.
So let's go back to those two beings conceived at the beginning of this talk.
We have two beings both conceived in the middle of 1979 on the exact same day.
Let's imagine one of them, Mary, is born three months prematurely.
So she's born on June 1st, 1980.
Henry by contrast is born a term so he's born on March 1st, 1980.
Simply by virtue of the fact that Mary was born prematurely three months she comes into
all sorts of rights three months earlier than Henry does.
The right to consent to sex, the right to vote, the right to drink.
Henry has to wait for all of that not because he's actually any different in age biologically
except in terms of when he was born.
We find other kinds of weirdness in terms of what their rights are.
Henry by virtue of being assumed to be male, although I haven't told you that he's the
XY one, by virtue of being assumed to be male is now liable to be drafted which Mary does
not have to worry about.
Mary meanwhile cannot in all the states have the same right that Henry has in all the states,
namely the right to marry.
Henry can marry in every state a woman but Mary can only marry today in a few states
a woman.
So we have these anatomical categories that persist that are in many ways sort of problematic
and questionable and the question to me becomes what do we do as our science gets to be so
good in looking at anatomy that we reach the point where we have to admit that a democracy
that's been based on anatomy might start falling apart.
I don't want to give up the science but at the same time it kind of feels sometimes like
the science is coming out from under us.
So where do we go?
It seems like what happens in our culture is a sort of pragmatic attitude.
We have to draw the line somewhere so we will draw the line somewhere but a lot of people
get stuck in a very strange position.
So for example Texas has at one point decided that what it means to marry a man is to mean
that you don't have a Y chromosome and what it means to marry a woman means you do have
a Y chromosome.
Now in practice they don't actually test people for their chromosomes but this is also very
bizarre because of the story I told you at the beginning about androgen sensitivity syndrome.
If we look at one of the founding fathers of modern democracy Dr. Martin Luther King
he offers us something of a solution in his eye of a dream speech.
He says we should judge people based not on the color of their skin but on the content
of their character moving beyond anatomy and I want to say yeah that sounds like a really
good idea but in practice how do you do it?
How do you judge people based on the content of character?
I also want to point out that I'm not sure that is how we should distribute rights in
terms of humans because I have to admit there are some golden retrievers that I know that
are probably more deserving of social services than some humans I know.
I want to also say there are probably also even some yellow Labradors that I know that
are more capable of informed intelligent mature decisions about sexual relations than some
40 year olds that I know.
So how do we operationalize the question of content of character?
It turns out to be really difficult and part of me also wonders what if content of character
turns out to be something that's scannable in the future, able to be seen with an fMRI?
Do we really want to go there?
I'm not sure where we go.
What I do know is that it seems really important to think about the idea of the United States
being in the lead of thinking about this issue of democracy.
We've done a really good job struggling with democracy and I think we would do a good job
in the future.
We don't have the situation that Iran has, for example, where a man who's sexually attracted
to other men is liable to be murdered unless he's willing to submit to a sex change, in
which case he's allowed to live.
We don't have that kind of situation.
I'm glad to say we don't have the kind of situation with a surgeon I talked to a few
years ago who had brought over a set of conjoined twins in order to separate them, partly to
make a name for himself.
But when I was on the phone with him asking why he was going to do the surgery, this was
a very high-risk surgery, his answer was that in this other nation these children were
going to be treated very badly and so he had to do this.
My response to him was, well, have you considered political asylum instead, instead of a separation
surgery?
The United States has offered tremendous possibility for allowing people to be the way they are
without having them to have to be changed for the sake of the state.
So I think we have to be in the lead.
Well, just to close, I want to suggest to you that I've been talking a lot about the
fathers and I want to think about the possibilities of what democracy might look like or might
have looked like if we had more involved the mothers.
And I want to say something a little bit radical for a feminist and that is that I think that
there may be different kinds of insights that can come from different kinds of anatomies,
particularly when we have people thinking in groups.
Now for years, because I've been interested in intersex, I've also been interested in
sex difference research.
And one of the things I've been really interested in is looking at the differences between males
and females in terms of the way they think and operate in the world.
And what we know from cross-cultural studies is that females on average, not everyone,
but on average are more inclined to be very attentive to complex social relations and
to taking care of people who are basically vulnerable within the group.
And so if we think about that, we have an interesting situation on our hands.
Years ago when I was in graduate school, one of my graduate advisors who knew I was interested
in feminism and considered myself a feminist, as I still do, asked a really strange question.
He said, tell me what's feminine about feminism.
And I thought, well, that's the dumbest question I've ever heard.
Feminism is all about undoing stereotypes about gender.
So there's nothing feminine about feminism.
But the more I thought about his question, the more I thought there might be something
feminine about feminism.
That is to say, there might be something on average different about female brains from
male brains that makes us more attentive to deeply complex social relationships and more
attentive to taking care of the vulnerable.
So whereas the fathers were extremely attentive to figuring out how to protect individuals
from the state, it's possible that if we injected more mothers into this concept, what we would
have is more of a concept of not just how to protect, but how to care for each other.
And maybe that's where we need to go in the future when we take democracy beyond anatomy
is to think less about the individual body in terms of the identity and think more about
those relationships so that as we the people try to create a more perfect union, we're
thinking about what we do for each other.
Thank you.